Guide to the Joe Vincent Meigs Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Joe Vincent Meigs papers
1858-1915
MS 334
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11
The papers consist of correspondence, pamphlets, scrapbooks, genealogical materials and papers related to the Meigs Transit System in Boston and the American Civil War, including the formation of a black light artillery battalion. Meigs' Civil War service in the Tennessee army is documented in correspondence, a memoir, and a scrapbook. Meigs designed and installed his elevated rail system in 1885 and over 400 drawings as well as other materials connected with the enterprise are included in the papers. The correspondence contains an extended series of letters from his father, Return Jonathan Meigs, written between 1858 and 1888, as well as substantial genealogical correspondence.
Meigs, Joe V. (Joe Vincent), 1840-
Existence and Location of Copies
Scrapbook of materials related to Meigs elevated railway is available on microfilm from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM202. 1987. 507 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1959 or 1961 from Ed Morrill. Gift of Liz Courtney, 1985. Gift of Charles M. Sullivan, 2006. For information prior to the purchase of the Meigs material, see the dealers records at BRBL, Morrill file, 1958-1959.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Joe Vincent Meigs (1840-) Papers contain material relating primarily to three different areas: the Meigs Rapid Transit System, the U.S. Civil War, and family genealogies. Meigs designed an "extraordinary" type of elevated railway—described best in his pamphlet in the folder "Misc. re Meigs Rapid Transit,1," in Box 7—which was installed in Boston on a limited scale in 1884. (The line failed quickly, but not because of engineering difficulties; rather because funds were lacking.)
During the Civil War, Captain Meigs served in the loyal Tennessee army. His war service, including his formation and leadership of what he believed to be the first black light artillery battalion and his invention of a cartridge is documented in his pamphlet, "Some Events of His Life;" correspondence; and a scrapbook. The Civil War scrapbook (in the 1986 addition to the papers) is a particularly rich source and primarily documents the administration, composition, disciplinary matters and complaints about some soldiers. Additional topics include Lincoln's assassination and Butler's death. The scrapbook includes correspondence, official documents, memorabilia, notes, and photographs. Of particular note are the letters from Meigs to his father; letters from Abraham Lincoln, Andrew Johnson, G. W. Mercer, and R. D. Mussey; muster rolls; "Colored Recruits Wanted! For the Light Artillery Service," a recruitment poster; a few photographs; equipment lists, and ordinance stores.
Meigs' genealogical interests ran wide and deep. In this collection are many letters relating directly to genealogies, along with genealogical charts and books. Among the families covered are: Benton, Bishop, Clendinen, Love, McCulloch, McSpalden, Meggs, Meigs, Pope, and van Bibber. Meigs published books on his genealogical findings, three of his books being in the Yale University Library.
Biographical / Historical
Josiah (Joe) Vincent Meigs was born on June 7, 1840, one of five sons of Return Jonathan and Eugenia (Love) Meigs. Joe Meigs spent his childhood in Nashville, Tennessee, where his father was a prominent jurist.
In 1858 R. J. Meigs apprenticed Joe to his brother James, an engineer for the Memphis and Charlestown railroad. When war broke out, Joe left Memphis and returned to Nashville. His father's strong unionist feelings forced the family to flee Tennessee in 1861. After a few years in New York, Joe Meigs went to Washington, D.C., where his father was clerk for the Supreme Court of the District of Columbia, and got a position as clerk in the office of the Secretary of War. After a year in this post, Meigs joined the Union forces, and with the help of influential connections made through his father, he was able to raise the first black light artillery battalion. Despite his success with the battalion, he was forced to resign his commission due to injuries.
A job in the court of claims in Washington provided minimal financial support for Meigs while he worked at his true vocation: invention. General Benjamin Butler became interested in Meigs' talents as an inventor, especially in gun and cartridge design. In 1866 the Meigs family moved to Lowell, Massachusetts, under Butler's patronage, and Meigs became manager of the U.S. Cartridge Co.
Meigs' interest in traction problems, first contemplated when he was a boy and fine tuned while at work as a young man on the Memphis and Charlestown Railroad, led to the development of a monorail railway system which Meigs felt would revolutionize rapid transit. With General Butler's financial backing, Meigs and others began in 1881 the difficult task of seeking permission to build an elevated railway in Boston. Opposition by street car lobbyists kept a charter from being granted until 1884. In order to encourage capital investment and to fulfill one of the terms of the 1884 charter, the Meigs Elevated Railway Construction Company was founded in Cambridge, Massachusetts. By 1885-1886, one-third mile of track had been laid and an engine, tender, and car were operational.
By 1887 the elevated railway was both an engineering and a popular success. Lack of financial support, however, and continued opposition from street railways interests plagued Meigs and his enterprise.
Years of legal battles resulted in approval for the Meigs-Subway bill in 1894. Unfortunately Meigs' refusal to accept electricity as the chief source of motive power for the railway lost him financial support. By 1896 Meigs sold his charter rights to the elevated railway line.
In the last years of his life, Meigs immersed himself in gathering genealogical information on the Meigs family. In failing health from his Civil War injuries, Meigs died from a stroke on November 14, 1907, in Charlestown, Massachusetts.
[Biographical information extracted from a prospectus by Tawny Ryan Nelb.]
Business; Local transit; Monorail railroads; Railroads, Elevated; Boston (Mass.); Lowell (Mass.); New England; Tennessee -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Inventors; Soldiers; Meigs, Joe V. (Joe Vincent), 1840-; Meigs, Return J. (Return Jonathan), 1801-1891; Meigs family
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - R. J. Meigs to J. V. Meigs, 1858-1870 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
    - R. J. Meigs to J. V. Meigs, 1871-1888 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
    - Mrs. Mary Langley, 1905-1907 October (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Mrs. Sarah N. Love, Circa 1907 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Capt. John A. McNeil, 1906-1907 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Meigs H. Whaples
      - 1903-1905 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Re: genealogies, 1905-1907 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Re: Meigs' cartridge, Circa 1865 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Re: pension, 1864-1907 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes correspondence with Mr. Baldwin, Mr. Thompson and Congressmen Powers and Weeks.
  - The Hildreth Homestead (poem), 1899 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Certain Events of His Life", Circa 1864 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Genealogical material (Box 4)
  - Material re Meigs Rapid Transit (Box 5–6)
  - Material re Meigs Rapid Transit and misc (Box 7)
  - Genealogical correspondence (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, mostly genealogical (Box 9)
  - One book of correspondence (Box 10)
  - One book of correspondence (Box 11)
  - Photograph of "Reception to the Philadelphia City Council of the Meigs Elevated R.R. Construction Co. East Cambridge, Mass. 1887 May 27," with negative [Folio] (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous blank office forms of the Memphis and Charleston Rail Road [Folio] (Box 13)
  - Hand lettered signs on the "Meigs System" (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter on railroad (Box 13)
  - Ms list of various railroad section, 1 leaf (Box 13)
  - Blueprints and mechanical drawings [Folios] (Box 14–23)
  - Scrapbook of materials related to the Meigs elevated railway [ca. 1875-1890s]. [Original scrapbook pages were discarded after filming in 1987. See Film HM 202] (Reel 1)
- Additional Material, 1863-1904; Accession 1986-M-115
  - Civil War scrapbook, 1863-1865 (Box 1, Folder 1a-1h)
  - "Meigs Elevated Railway", Circa 1896 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    An album of mounted photographs by Henry B. Harrington.
  - "The Meigs Elevated Railway System," by Joe V. Meigs, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles of Agreement and letter, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Henry Dobbs, et als v. Francis H. Peabody, et als, 1900 December 3-4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Transcript of cross examination of Henry Dobbins.
  - Letter of appointment for Joseph V. Meigs, Jr. (son) as associate medical examiner of Middlesex County, Massachusetts, 1905 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Fifty Years of Unified Transportation in Metropolitan Boston", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Additional Material, 1880, 1885, 1911-1915; Accession 2006-M-112
  - Meigs, Eugenia
    - Correspondence, incoming, 1911-1915, n.y., undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 6)
    - Diary [includes loose photograph], 1911 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Drawings of various components of the Meigs railway system, 1880, 1885 (Box 2–4)